BU Records: O.H. Cooper, Inclusive: 1899-1902, Bulk: 1899-1902
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: O.H. Cooper
Inclusive: 1899-1902, Bulk: 1899-1902
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/139
Cooper, O.H., 1852 - 1932
2 document boxes
The BU Records: O.H. Cooper contain personal correspondence, a financial ledger, three books of letters, and printed materials collected by former Baylor President Oscar Henry (O. H.) Cooper.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Oscar Henry Cooper, who was often referred to as O. H. Cooper by his contemporaries, was born in Panola County, Texas, to Dr. William Henry and Katherine Rosser Cooper on 1852 November 22. His long academic record shows him to be a brilliant scholar as well as a noted public educator in the United States and Germany. After studying for two years at Marshall University, Cooper transferred and completed his undergraduate work at Yale University where he graduated as the valedictorian of the class of 1872. His prolific work in the educational field included teaching positions at Henderson Male and Female College (1873-1879), Sam Houston Normal Institute (2 years), and a return to Yale University. He received his graduate education while attending the University of Berlin from 1884 to 1885. Upon returning to the United States, Cooper pursued teaching positions at the secondary level, working as the principal of Houston High School, the Texas State Superintendent of Public Instruction, and the superintendent of Galveston-area schools (1890-1896). Amidst all these career pursuits, on 1886 November 24, Cooper married Mary Brian Stewart. They had four children.
Cooper’s success as an educator and his devotion to his Baptist roots led to his appointment as the President of Baylor University from 1899 to 1902. With Cooper as President, Baylor gained national acclaim. Most of the school’s degrees were recognized for the first time by the more established eastern universities, the Department of Pedagogy was officially created, and the Department of Theology was expanded. The school also received substantial grants and scholarships during this period including $75,000 each from F.L. Carroll and his son George to build a chapel, library, and science building. These were the largest donations in Texas school history at the time. In 1914, Baylor University awarded Cooper an honorary doctoral degree.
The story of Cooper’s resignation from Baylor University is odd for such a distinguished teacher and leader. According to Baylor University’s website, a couple of students snuck a dog into chapel service one day. When the dog started barking, Cooper became enraged and threw the dog out a window from the third floor. Students protested the act, and Cooper resigned on 1902 March 31.
He then went on to Simmons College from 1902 to 1909, enjoying similar successes. From 1909 to 1915, Cooper established a school for boys in Abilene. His last position before retirement was at the University of Texas at Austin. Cooper had been instrumental in the establishment of the University of Texas in Austin during the 1880s, and later served as a professor of history and the philosophy of education there. Cooper died in Abilene, Texas, on 1932 August 22.
Scope and Content
The BU Records: O.H. Cooper begin in 1899 with letters of correspondence and continues throughout Cooper’s tenure as the head of Baylor University. The bulk of the collection is correspondence pertaining to the business side of his position.
This collection was originally named BU Records of the Office of the President-Oscar Henry Cooper, 1899-1902. During the processing stage, this name was shortened to BU Records: O.H. Cooper. The subject’s first and middle name were abbreviated, because President Cooper went by the name O. H. Cooper.
Arrangement
The current organization of the BU Records: O.H. Cooper reflects the original provenance. Currently the records are arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, II. Financial Documents, and III. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/139. Acquired 1974-09-00
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Samuel Palmer Brooks papers, Inclusive: 1880-1937, Bulk: 1913-1931
Rufus Columbus Burleson papers, Inclusive: 1836-1966, undated, Bulk: 1891-1897
Related references
“Oscar Henry Cooper.” Baylor Unviersity. Accessed 2012 January 19.
Stookey, Stephen M. “Oscar Henry Cooper.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 January 19.
Turner, Thomas. The Presidents of Baylor University. Waco: Baylor University, 1981.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Cooper, Oscar H. (Oscar Henry), 1852-1932.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.; Baylor University -- Presidents.
Subjects
Education, Higher -- Texas -- History.
Genres
Correspondence.; Financial records.; Transcripts.
- Correspondence, 1899-1900, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Excellent.
  Biography/Profile
  The correspondence series, the largest series in the collection, includes letters to and from former Baylor President O. H. Cooper. Most of the letters are exchanged between Cooper and potential employees. This series is in excellent condition.
  - General, 1899 February-October (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 1899 November-1900 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1900 January 26-February (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General, 1900 March (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General, 1900 April 2-25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General, 1900 April 25-May 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General, 1900 May 21-29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General, 1900 May 29-June, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Financial Documents, undated; 2
  General condition: Poor.
  The series includes one item: a financial ledger. It is, however, in poor condition.
  - Ledger, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Literary Productions, 1899-1902, undated; 3
  General condition: Average.
  The literary productions series contains a folder of printed materials and three books containing transcriptions of Cooper’s personal correspondence. This series is in average to good condition.
  - Printed Materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Book: Letters, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Book: Letters, 1900-1901 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Book: Letters, 1899-1902 (Box 2, Folder 2)